Ellen Fenton Diaries of Travels to Boulogne-sur-Mer
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Diaries
  - Diary, 1854 August 23-September 14; Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813; 1 volume (128 pages); 19 pages of watercolor drawings; 1 funeral notice; 1 playbill; 32.5 x 20.5 cm. (Box Vol. 1)
    Fenton is witness to the historic visit of Prince Albert and Emperor Louis Napoleon to Boulogne in early September, 1854, reported in contemporary British periodicals (see Illustrated London News ). Meeting at Paris, Albert and Louis Napoleon III made an official visit to inspect the Northern French camps. The British had recently allied with France against Prussia, and the official meeting marked a turning point in diplomatic relations between the once-hostile powers. On the 5th of September, the family boards the Albion steamship to watch the Prince and Emperor's arrival. Fenton, placed up on a high point, thinks she sees the Prince look in her direction as the local crowd cheers. Fenton judges the Emperor as "dreadfully, painfully cunning" in contrast to the Prince's demure "flush, that made him look just like [Franz Xaver] Wintershalter's picture, taken before his marriage" (47). In addition to military processions and official ceremony in connection with the war, Fenton also witnesses invalid soldiers carried in "Ambulances" (see drawing), "said to have cholera" (13). Infectious diseases, cholera principle among them, claimed more British, French, and Russian soldiers' lives than fatal wounds during the 1854-1856 period of the Crimean war (Gill and Gill 1801).
    Fear of the recent cholera outbreak seems to preoccupy Fenton's discussions of her family's illnesses. Her servant, Margaret, falls ill frequently, and among her children, Dick falls especially ill. "Everyone says the Cholera is raging, and I have a sense of constant responsibility, when I notice that the lower part of our house seems very badly drained" (84). Fenton treats her children and servants with homeopathic remedies in the form of "globules." Despite her fears of cholera, Fenton doesn't seem to fear venturing out of doors. With her familiarity of French idiom, Fenton is quite at ease making the acquaintance of Boulogne locals. She particularly admires independent spirit in certain Boulogne women, especially the spirited Marie Fournier. Market women and "porteuses" girls also seem to serve Fenton's penchant for portrait sketches. She forms an attachment with a young porteuse, Josephine, as well as staff at a hotel she discovers during one of her daily wanderings. During Prince Albert's visit, she also finds herself amongst a crowd of sailors: "matelots and matelottes… in full costume," who crowd around her with questions.
    Fenton and her family take frequent trips to the "sands" and to the "bains." Boulogne was popular for its baths since the late eighteenth-century, when M. Clery de Becourt, following a voyage to Italy where he had visited many 'établissements de bains de mer,' resolved to create a similar warm-water bathing établissement (Splingard 10). On occasion, the Fentons hire a carriage to take them on country drives, which causes Fenton to reminisce about her childhood days in Boulogne. One long excursion to the Vallée du Nacre for the day results in a lengthy description of the outing, the farms they visit, the rustic scenery and picnic lunch. This outing also provides many sketching opportunities for Fenton, who draws not only the local peasant women but also the visiting bourgeois strollers (see drawings, this volume). Fenton demonstrates remarkable calm when the family is stranded for a few hours while waiting for a coach to bring them to Boulogne at day's end.
    A community of English sojourners in Boulogne are frequently mentioned as part of the family's daily social calls: Mr. and Mrs. Newte, John and Caroline Emmett, Caroline and Charles Venables, and Mr. and Mrs. Burton. Particularly humorous incidences involve Mrs. Burton, who lands on the Fentons' doorstep expecting lodging, and who can't seem to escape Fenton's sardonic characterizations.
    Cholera; Watercolors; Travel sketches -- France; Boulogne-sur-Mer (France) -- Description and travel; Boulogne-sur-Mer (France) -- Views; Crimean War, 1853-1856; Diaries; Napoleon, Emperor of the French, III, 1808-1873; Albert, Prince Consort, consort of Victoria, Queen of Great Britain, 1819-1861; Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813 -- Diaries
  - Diary, 1854 September 14-22; Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813; 1 volume (102 pages); 14 pages of watercolor drawings; 1 receipt; c. 32.5 x 20.5 cm. (Box Vol. 2)
    Continuation of Ellen Fenton's holograph diary detailing her family vacation at Boulogne-sur-Mer, 1854. Includes fourteen pages of watercolor drawings of local people, scenery and landscapes, all of which illustrate journal descriptions. Also includes one receipt for "Lemoisson-Desille, Porcelaine, Cristaux, et Verrerie." Inscribed on back cover: "Written by Ellen Fenton, Haven Green House, Ealing, London, 1854."
    Volume 2 picks up Fenton's journal in mid-September of 1854, with a discussion of the cholera outbreak. She has "heard the four people died last night, of cholera, in one house, a few doors off" (p. 1). Fenton and her family witness several funeral processions, and there is steady activity at the nearby St. Nicolas church. Fenton takes her children on several visits to the church, where she is struck by the number of coffins. She remarks, "The whole was terrifying, and… when it burst over me, that as no one was there, no doubt they went on to the side altar, because it would be dangerous to stay so near the coffins" (4). Fenton takes great care in describing the priests, their dress, the altar decoration, and choir boys. The scene seems to capture Fenton's active imagination, for soon after, she spends a sleepless night convinced that the sound of heavy knocking coming from the direction of the church is a cholera victim trapped alive in one of the coffins. "I resolved to take a blanket – but then – what should I do? If he had died of Cholera, who would open their Doors to him? Of course, I ought to bring him here, out on the drawing room sofa, until day, I ought to give him hot drinks" (6). She learns the next day that a soldier had been arrested and locked up in the vaults beneath the church because it was too late to bring him to the citadel to be imprisoned.
    Despite the frequent funeral services opposite their house, Fenton does not dwell on gloomy subjects. She turns to more lighthearted matters, such as the purchase of music scores for Clara ("Les Noces de Jeannette" and "Cours mon Aiguille") as well as light-hearted descriptions of her son, Dick, in his various sentinel costumes of ribband, giving salutations to passing officers (see accompanying drawing). She brings her family to hear the Guide band perform at the colonnade, including a colorful account and a sketch of the scene. Her reports of dress and costume range from rote description to witty derision. Upon her note of some "extravagantly fashionable dress, upon very ugly women," she singles out one particular woman, "wonderfully ugly, and yet [who] dared to wear her hair à l'Imperatrice, with favorits" (12).
    Fenton plays frequent host to Mrs. Newte and Mrs. Burton, both of whom, fallen on hard times, Fenton feels obliged to feed and entertain. The servant Mrs. Newte, called "Griffin," particularly amuses Fenton, as he is dressed "as a nobleman," (12) despite not having any income from his impoverished employers. A visit to Notre Dame basilica with Mrs. Burton and Mrs. Newte provides another opportunity for lighthearted observation and an accompanying sketch. When they are asked to pay one franc each to climb the narrow network of lathes and scaffolding to the dome, Fenton and the others are incredulous: "Poor blind Mr. [Frederick] Newte, his delicate wife, fat Mrs. Burton and Mrs Newte and her bellyache. Gradually they all saw how absurd it was." Mrs. Newte's young charge and servant, Kitty Kirby, captivates Fenton's attention, and she 'borrows' her for a portrait (see Volume 1). Fenton waxes lyrical: "I felt just as if some being from a fairer world had come to me, when the influence of Kitty Kirby, beauty & sweet innocence came over me, as I painted her. The delicacy of her face, manner & whole look… I was affected to tears, & laid my head on my hands, crying, for also her tale is so sad" (23).
    Fenton's forwardness and fluency in French result in frequent, colourful encounters with local shopkeepers and venders. She remarks, "I have had many such chats, across counters, here, and have been astonished at the high moral tone these people seem to have generally" (31). After talking with one shopwoman, Fenton is invited to return to the shop after hours to dine. She and Dall head to the scullery, where she is greeted by a hearty Boulonnais meal: "the most tender of Jelly – like of Bouville, with a wonderful gravy, served in a cup, of all oddities. Potatoes, browned, and Harricots in a exquisite white sauce, which seemed to me made of Fowl bones & Ham, and sprinkled with parsley" (33). When at another shop, the woman behind the counter speaks of her admiration of English puddings, so Fenton feels compelled to provide a lengthy description of how to make boiled suet and boiled head pudding.
    Fenton makes note that her eldest daughter, Clara, is beginning to attract attention. On a trip to the esplanade, the crowd of people turn to stare: "I found this was regarded as a debut of Care's [Clara's]… Her bloom was beautiful." (39). During this time amongst the crowd, Clara accidently drops a bag of thirty francs, which Fenton laments is "no trifle these few days, I meant to wind up with such economy & caution" (41). Relying on her circle of English friends for loans, particularly Charles Venebles, Fenton is able to scrape by during the last few days of the family's stay at Boulogne, until the bag is safely retrieved with the help of a town crier.
    The Fenton family's final Boulogne excursion of 1854 is to the Fort on Mont Lambert. Reading Monteith's Guide to Boulogne, Fenton and her children are enticed by the romance of the fort, purported built by Henry VIII and restored by Napoleon Bonaparte but "now, a ruin" (46). With a large party of servants and children in tow, Fenton sets out on foot with her large cartridge paper and drawing materials, "finding excuses for climbing the steep almost perpendicular sides of the mont" and engaging in make-believe gun-fire like soldiers (50). Fenton insists that they spend overnight in the fort, but the darkening clouds and lightning prevents her from realizing her plan. Fenton takes the opportunity to observe the sublimity of the scene, descending into the dark moat alone where she finds a "change from the gay laughter of our little party, to the silence – the change from rich sunset to lowering dusk. How solemn the spot had become." (53, see accompanying drawing).
    Fenton talks very little about her husband. Though she never describes any wayward feelings for other men, she does delight in the occasional flirtatious encounter, and seems to note awkward run-ins with a "Mr. Mayhew." On the steamship journey homeward, Fenton and her family spend the day with "Frank Stone, the artist"(62), who asks to see one of her views. Frank Stone may be the same English painter who led the attack against the Pre-Raphaelite brotherhood. The final pages of the volume are devoted to Fenton's remembrances of Boulogne upon her return to Ealing. It also describes her gratitude to her brother, Maurice Emmett, whom she notes "forced upon me – as also last year – the extra money which enabled me to have indulgences and luxuries" (64). About one week after the family returns to England, Maurice takes Dick with him to Paris, stopping in Boulogne along the way.
    Crimean War, 1853-1856; Cholera; Watercolors; Travel sketches -- France; Boulogne-sur-Mer (France) -- Description and travel; Diaries; Boulogne-sur-Mer (France) -- Views; Stone, Frank; Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813 -- Diaries
  - Diary, 1856 August 2-August 20; Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813; 1 volume (122 pages); 25 pages of watercolor drawings; 1 program; c. 32.5 x 20.5 cm. (Box Vol. 3)
    Holograph diary describing Ellen Fenton's family vacation at Boulogne-sur-Mer, 1857. Includes twenty-five pages of watercolor drawings of local people, scenery and landscapes to accompany journal descriptions. This volume includes a program for the "Procession Générale de l'Assomption et de la Station en l'honneur de N. – D. de Boulogne," which Fenton also translates into English (with her own annotations), bound with the journal.
    In her entry for Saturday August 2nd, 1856, Fenton reports the family's bustling preparations for their upcoming trip to Boulogne. She has been working with a "Mme Leslie" and "Mrs. Macleod" on finishing her batch of needlework and reports the preparation of a vast provisions basket. She reports that "Lattoo Macleod" was to go with them on this trip. The voyage is very difficult; Fenton describes the bad smell, the stifling heat, the fidgety and sick children (particularly Dall), and her baby's cries, which prevent her from enjoying the vessel's approach at Boulogne. Fenton finds clean, airy lodgings over a bootmaker who used to work for her father thirty years prior.
    Fenton hires a French 'matelotte' attendant, Louise, during the family's stay at Boulogne. Louise is the subject of Fenton's consternation and amusement. Fenton marvels at Louise's strange cleaning habits. When Fenton requests that the carpets be lifted, she is awed by Louise's odd way of washing the dust without sweeping first. Likewise, she remarks "Louise does her work so strangely – to avoid coming at night on Sunday, when she goes to dance." Fenton is very pleased with a large-scale painting she completes of Louise, which she frames for her house (see vol. 2). The other servant Charlotte, whom Fenton brings to Boulogne for the first time, is also the subject of occasional ridicule. Fenton delights in her culture shock, noting her 'ecstacies' over the sandhills, and her 'shock' at seeing white flannelled nuns. In preparation to watch one of the processions, Fenton reports that "Good Charlotte was in terrible trouble & engrossment because her dress was not clean & her bonnet not an holiday one" (p. 57). To Clara's "indignation", Fenton bids her go home to put on one of her daughter's cotton skirts, leaving Fenton alone to manage the children.
    After a few days alone with the children, "Appa" joins them, looking pale from the sea voyage. Fenton complains that "as usual - the wet blanket" found fault with the house she had chosen. When they dine at the Hotel du Rhin, Fenton enjoys proving to the proprietress, Mme Florent, that she has a "live husband" but as an aside, prides herself on her un-chaperoned independence: "Appa always says, my travelling without a gentleman is wrong. However I prefer it" (31). She later reveals her thoughts on the sobering effect of her husband's presence: "It is surprising how tame and conventional Appa makes us all, directly he comes. I own I lose interest in my travels… One feature is the orderly absence of the children and their dear uproar, which gives such spirit to all, through their being so full of interest & wonder in all about them" (35). When the family takes "Appa" to see Mont Lambert, Fenton regrets his reluctance to climb the plateau, for fear of becoming "giddy" (68). He misses the grand view from the top, which Fenton records in a sketch. She is self-conscious of her own capacity to record the surrounding landscape, remarking: "What a beautiful view we had of the Fôret de Boulogne! It was too extensive for my paper – too full of dreams, imagination and poetry for my pencil. The light and shade (so gently varied), so rich and mysterious, of deep dark woods, was not to be attempted by my sacrilegious hand" (69).
    With "Dick," Fenton sees the well-known actress Madame Ristori perform in Francesca da Rimini, producing a sketch of Ristori "before the curtain" receiving bouquets (33). At the theatre, she awkwardly runs into "Mayhew" whom she reveals as Rev'd Mr Hunt, a gentleman she traveled with in 1853 (other awkward encounters occur in the 1854 volumes). She also bumps into a woman she can't recognize and, revealing her intended readership, announces: "She was a lady we knew through you, dear Mrs Ibotson, just before we left Notting Hill" (34).
    The Venebles warn Fenton of an epidemic spreading around Boulogne. When "Tinny" (Frederick) comes down with throat and chest pain, Fenton worries it is the "scourge" (75). She seeks out a homeopathic chemist, administers her own "globules" and consults the Venebles' homeopathic reference book. These bouts of illness do not prevent Fenton from venturing out, however, when she is compelled to witness prizes handed out at the College Communale, which she describes with great relish. She is drawn to other award ceremonies, such as the Abbé Haffringue's, which feeds her desire for spectacle. Fred's illness makes the Fentons discuss leaving Boulogne, but the little boy soon rallies.
    The family watches the many processions and festivals of the season, including the celebration of Napoleon's birthday, coinciding with the festival of the Virgin, which Fenton speculates is "perhaps to satisfy those who would not assist to keep Napoleon's fête" (56). Fenton includes the order of procession, translated and hand-written from the French program with annotations. (The original French program is also included at the end of the volume). Fenton stands on a balcony watching the great "uproar" amidst a group of artillery men. She contrasts the loud assembly to the "calm dignity in our churches" (59). Fenton goes to great lengths to describe the costumes of the crowd, the groups of young ladies whom she calls "Houris", the rows of nuns, and the "English converts," or "perverts."
    Travel sketches -- France; Watercolors; Boulogne-sur-Mer (France) -- Description and travel; Boulogne-sur-Mer (France) -- Views; Diaries; Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813 -- Diaries
  - Diary, 1856 August 20-September 2; Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813; 1 volume (100 pages), 20 pages of watercolor drawings; 4 receipts; 3 playbills; 1 letter; 1 musical score; c. 32.5 x 20.5 cm. (Box Vol. 4)
    A continuation of Ellen Fenton's holograph journal describing a family vacation at Boulogne-sur-Mer, 1857. Includes twenty pages of watercolor drawings of local people, scenery and landscapes to accompany journal descriptions. This volume contains three playbills, for: Une femme qui se jette par la fenetre, La Dame de St-Tropez, and Le Bonhomme Jadis. Also containing: a letter from Mr. Atkinson; a hand-drawn music score "From Memory" for "The Tantillerie [sic] Polka – 3rd September, 1856," a tune Fenton recalls hearing at a ball described in this volume; a funeral announcement for Jean-Philippe Rigaut; four miscellaneous receipts.
    Fenton receives a letter from her husband giving account of the unpleasant steamship voyage back to England, recounting that "nearly every lady was sick" and that one of the seats came away from its fastening in the middle of the voyage, tossing invalids about. Hearing that a new cathedral bell has just arrived at Boulogne, Fenton hurries to the train station hoping to catch a glimpse of a gigantic bell, but finds "amid a confusion of straw, hay and rubbish, stood a modest little brass bell, of about – at most, two feet high!" (81). Nevertheless, Fenton later enjoys watching the procession of the bell to the cathedral, conducted by four hundred "pelerins" (pilgrims) walking barefoot (104). She sketches many of the pilgrims who crowd the streets, including one "whom we supposed a great sinner." The procession ends at the Cathedral, where all gather to hear a sermon and afterwards dine at the Table d'Hôtes, much to the proprieter's chagrin. With her three eldest children on donkeys, Fenton visits Ostrohove to see Fanny Crawford. She describes Fanny's house as "very unenglish" (82), and marvels at the arrangement of furniture, the French and German lithographs, and the "foreign way of dining" (83). In the company of her childhood friend, Fenton is reminded of "dear Mrs. Wolley in her way and manner," perhaps a reference to Fanny's mother (85). The next day Fenton visits an engraving shop on the Grande Rue, where she is surprised to find the shop woman remembers her. Notably, she omits the detail (included in the draft copy) in this journal version that "she knew me as John [Emmett's] sister, and that "vous n'êtes plus amies!!! [you are no longer friends!!!]" She retains details about their discussion about the artist Millais.
    Fenton takes any opportunity to discuss religion with the local population. She engages her hairdresser in a long conversation about Catholicism, reporting that "the Priests had disgusted him, altogether, with religion that a passion for rule and money, governed them" (86). She says he felt that the general population was deprived of education by the clergy. Likewise, Mme Florent of the Hotel du Rhin criticizes the priests for making people "so superstitious, that they would become nothing but fools" (87). Fenton takes this opportunity to preach the Bible: "I believed it my duty… to take my own interpretation of it – to stand or fall by it" (87). Suspicious of anyone remotely associated with the Catholic church, Fenton believes that an overly friendly mason working at the cathedral "was appointed by the Priests, to charm us 'heretics'" (132).